Guide to the William Michael Rossetti Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Michael Rossetti collection
1857-1910
GEN MSS 269
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.2
(1 box)
Letters by Rossetti to various parties, including James Jackson Jarves and Eric Sutherland Robertson; two manuscript pieces: a "brief critique of British artists exhibiting in a British exhibition touring America," and an essay on Ruskin; and a signature clipped from a letter.
Rossetti, William Michael, 1829-1919
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to William Michael Rossetti, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to June 1997 have been organized into three series. Series I, Correspondence, contains items written by Rossetti, including letters to a Miss Taylor, in London, regarding Percy Shelley. The two items in series II, Writings, are a critique of British artists and an essay on Ruskin. The Other Materials in series III consist solely of a signature clipped from a letter.
Authors, English -- 19th century; Jarves, James Jackson, 1818-1888; Robertson, Eric S(Eric Sutherland); Rossetti, William Michael, 1829-1919; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900
- I. Correspondence
  - ROSSETTI, WILLIAM MICHAEL
    - 2 ALS to L[ouis] C[harles] Alexander, London, 1888 Jan (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Concerning a committee for the benefit of Charles Mackay Purchase, 1956
    - ALS to [J. B. Bedford], London, n.y. Jan 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Gift, 1977
    - 2 ALS (postcards) to William Morris Colles, London, 1908, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Purchase, 1956
    - ALS to Miss Ulrica A. Fenwick, London, 1873 Jul 16 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - ALS to Mr. Herbert N. Flewker, London, 1889 Feb 23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Answering a request for an autograph. Purchase, 1956.
    - 2 ALS to James Jackson Jarves, London (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Purchase, 1946
    - ALS to John Nichol, London, 1881 Apr 8 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Purchase, 1954
    - ALS to Eric Robertson, [London], 1879 Sep 4 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Gift, 1983
    - 4 ALS to Eric Sutherland Robertson, London, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - ALS to William Smith [London], 1867 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      About a bust of Stothard. Gift, 1970
    - 3 ALS and 1 ALS (fragment) to Miss Taylor [London], 1880-[1881?] (Box 1, Folder 11)
      About the restoration of Percy Bysshe Shelley's tomb and the preparation of the adjoining grave for Edward John Trelawny's ashes, accompanied by 1 ALS from Rossetti to Trelawny, 12 November 1880, and a draft of a letter, unsigned, from Trelawny to Rossetti, 28 June 1879, on the same subject. Accompanied by drafts and translations of correspondence between Edward John Trelawny and John Trucchi, the Custodian of the English Cemetary at Rome about the repair of Shelley's tomb. Purchase, 1971,
    - ALS to Miss Taylor, London (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Accompanied by a draft of a letter composed by Rossetti for Edward John Trelawny to send to Lady Shelley. Purchase, 1971
    - ALS to Miss Taylor, London (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Concerning Edward John Trelawny's loan to Rossetti of a sofa once belonging to Percy Bysshe Shelley. Accompanied by a newspaper clipping about the sofa. Purchase, 1971
    - Envelope addressed to Edward John Trelawny, London, 1878 Dec 6 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Purchase, 1971
    - ALS to W. A. Turner, [London], 1884 Nov 5 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Gift, 1965
    - 5 ALS to Thomas J. Wise, London, 1889-92 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - ALS (fragment) to an unidentified recipient, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
      From a collection formed by George Bainton and William Michael Rossetti, Gift, 1957.
- II. Manuscripts, [1857-58]
  - "Brief critique of British artists exhibiting in a British exhibition touring America", autograph ms, [1857-58] (Box 1, Folder 18)
    List artists by number in a catalogue (not identified) with brief comments on their British and American reputations and their standing in the Pre-Raphaelite hierarchy; Holman Hunt, Barbara Bodichon, Ruskin, Linnell, and Ford Madox Brown are among those discussed. Purchase, 1955,
  - [Essay on Ruskin], AMS, 1908 Sep 11 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Purchase, 1965
- III. Other Materials, n.d.
  - Signature, clipped from letter addressed to Hallam Tennyson, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    From the S.C.G. Watkins Collection.